{
  "reference_number": "12203",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "Our primary focus should be on reducing domestic emissions. We should minimise our reliance on the purchase of international\n carbon units so we are not hamstrung by future fluctuations in carbon unit availability and prices."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only under clearly-defined exceptional circumstances, which still enable NZ to meet emissions targets consistent with achieving net-\n zero CO2 emissions by the time global warming reaches 2degC. Such circumstances would not include a change of Government."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only under clearly-defined exceptional circumstances e.g. significant natural disaster or recession. Rules should be defined so that\n subsequent carbon budgets essentially \"make up\" for any emission-reduction hiatus resulting from exceptional circumstances, to\n ensure the ultimate goal of Zero Carbon Bill is achieved. This should help incentivise early and strong measures for emission-\n\n reduction 'while the going is good', so we are positioned as well as possible in case of significant natural disaster etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Budgets must be set based off sound, internationally-accepted scientific evidence. The Government should keep abreast of\nwhat/how strongly-performing countries are achieving their emission reductions and strong economic performance, and collaborate\n\nwith these countries to ensure knowledge and learning is shared. Equally, we should observe other countries who are struggling with\nemission reduction and strong economic performance, and learn from their mistakes. As always, NZ Government must keep in mind\n\nthat NZ circumstances are unique; e.g. just because something is working well overseas, doesn't necessarily mean it will work well\nhere."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Expertise on sustaining and enhancing our natural environment and native biodiversity is a crucial component of our Climate Change\nCommission."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This is crucial as the climate is already changing and will continue to do so. Central Govt. needs to take charge and provide direction\nand leadership for the benefit of local Govt., sectors, businesses and communities."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Tourism is a huge and ever-growing component of our economy. Tourists are inherently high emitters of GHGs. This is exacerbated by\nNZ being a relatively isolated country geographically on a global scale (huge emissions required just to get here), as well as being a\n\nspread-out nation (high emissions required to explore our country), not to mention the emission-intensive nature of some tourist\nactivities (e.g. scenic flights). Perhaps the Government could consider some form of small visitor levy, the proceeds of which are used\nto contribute to forestry planting/purchasing international carbon units."
    }
  ]
}
